[
    {
        "id": 0,
        "question": "Player A declares an attack with their ${0} on a Monster Player B controls. On attack declaration, Player A activates the effect of ${0} to banish that opponent Monster. Does a replay occur?",
        "propositions": ["Yes", "No"],
        "correct": 0,
        "cards": ["Mirrorjade the Iceblade Dragon"],
        "links": ["https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17069&request_locale=en"],
        "explanation": "<p>A replay can only occur before the Damage Step starts.</p><p>When Player A attacks, a replay can occur in the following situations:</p><ul><li>● The number of Monsters on Player B changes (even momentarily)</li><li>● The attack target leaves the field</li><li>● The attacking Monster gains the ability to attack directly</li><li>● The attacking monster can no longer attack how it was attacking (mostly applies to a Monster that had the ability to attack directly but loses it, due to negation, etc.)</li></ul><p>In this case, the attack target left the field on attack declaration, so a replay can occur.</p>",
        "sources": ["Yu-Gi-Oh! Perfect Rulebook 2015, page 164"],
        "sources_links": ["https://ygorganization.com/perfectrulebook/"]
    },
    {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Player A declares an attack with their Monster on a Monster Player B controls. Before damage calculation, Player B activates ${0} by sending their Monster to the GY to negate the effects of Player A's Monster and halve its ATK. Does a replay occur?",
        "propositions": ["Yes", "No"],
        "correct": 1,
        "cards": ["Forbidden Droplet"],
        "links": ["https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=15299&request_locale=en"],
        "explanation": "<p>A replay can only occur before the Damage Step starts.</p><p>When Player A attacks, a replay can occur in the following situations:</p><ul><li>● The number of Monsters on Player B changes (even momentarily)</li><li>● The attack target leaves the field</li><li>● The attacking Monster gains the ability to attack directly</li><li>● The attacking monster can no longer attack how it was attacking (mostly applies to a Monster that had the ability to attack directly but loses it, due to negation, etc.)</li></ul><p>In this case, the attack target left the field during the \"Before damage calculation\" timing, which is during the Damage Step, so a replay cannot occur.</p>",
        "sources": ["Yu-Gi-Oh! Perfect Rulebook 2015, page 167", "Forbidden Droplet can be activated in Damage Step"],
        "sources_links": ["https://ygorganization.com/perfectrulebook/", "https://db.ygorganization.com/card#15299"]
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "Player A Special Summons ${0} while they have no Dragon Monsters in their Deck or GY. Can they activate the 2nd effect of that ${0}?",
        "propositions": ["Yes", "No"],
        "correct": 0,
        "cards": ["Bystial Magnamhut", "Infernoble Knight Captain Roland"],
        "links": ["https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17762&request_locale=en", "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=15275&request_locale=en"],
        "explanation": "<p>According to a precedent regarding the effect of ${1}, it is legal to activate an effect to add a card to your hand at a future point in the turn/duel, even if there are currently no cards that could be added. If no cards can be added when it is time to do so, then the effect will simply resolve without effect.</p>",
        "sources": ["Precedent for Captain Roland"],
        "sources_links": ["https://db.ygorganization.com/qa#23006"]
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "Player A declares a direct attack with their ${0} while Player B controls a Monster. On attack declaration, Player B activates their ${1} to negate the effects of Player A's ${0}. Does a replay occur?",
        "propositions": ["Yes", "No"],
        "correct": 0,
        "cards": ["Trickstar Lilybell", "Infinite Impermanence"],
        "links": ["https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=13045&request_locale=en", "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=13631"],
        "explanation": "<p>A replay can only occur before the Damage Step starts.</p><p>When Player A attacks, a replay can occur in the following situations:</p><ul><li>● The number of Monsters on Player B changes (even momentarily)</li><li>● The attack target leaves the field</li><li>● The attacking Monster gains the ability to attack directly</li><li>● The attacking monster can no longer attack how it was attacking (mostly applies to a Monster that had the ability to attack directly but loses it, due to negation, etc.)</li></ul><p>In this case, ${0} lost the ability to attack directly before the Damage Step started, so a replay can occur.</p>",
        "sources": ["Yu-Gi-Oh! Perfect Rulebook 2015, page 165"],
        "sources_links": ["https://ygorganization.com/perfectrulebook/"]
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "Player A declares a direct attack with their ${0} and proceeds to damage calculation successfully. After damage calculation, they activate the effect of that ${0} to send a \"Sky Striker\" card from their Deck to the GY. Which of the following card or effect can Player B activate in response to that effect?",
        "propositions": ["The 1st effect of ${1}","The 2nd effect of ${2}","The 1st effect of ${3} (assuming Player B controls no Monsters)","The 1st effect of ${4} (assuming Player B has a card in their hand)"],
        "correct": 2,
        "cards": ["Sky Striker Ace - Hayate", "Ash Blossom & Joyous Spring", "Therion \"King\" Regulus", "PSY-Framegear Gamma", "Grapha, Dragon Overlord of Dark World"],
        "links": [
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=13763&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=12950&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17119&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=12070&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17988&request_locale=en"
        ],
        "explanation": "<p>${0}'s effect happens \"After damage calcuation\", which is during the Damage Step. In general, Quick Effects cannot be activated during the Damage Step. However, Quick Effects that specifically negate the <i class=\"boldUnderline\">activation</i> of a card or effect can be activated during the Damage Step. Of the above cards' effects, the only one that negate the activation of an effect is ${3}, therefore is the only one that can be activated in this situtation.</p>",
        "sources": ["Yu-Gi-Oh! Perfect Rulebook 2017, page 112"],
        "sources_links": ["https://ygorganization.com/perfect-rulebook-2017/"]
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "Player A controls a Special Summoned Monster, activates ${0} and sends a Monster from their Deck to the GY, while Player B has ${1} and ${2} in their hand. Which effects can Player B trigger in a new chain after resolution?",
        "propositions": ["Only the 1st effect of ${1}, and the 1st effect of ${2} cannot be activated", "Only the 1st effect of ${2}, and the 1st effect of ${1} cannot be activated", "Only the 1st effect of ${1} OR only the 1st effect of ${2}", "Both the 1st effects of ${1} and ${2}"],
        "correct": 2,
        "cards": ["Foolish Burial", "Kelbek the Ancient Vanguard", "Agido the Ancient Sentinel", "Green Baboon, Defender of the Forest"],
        "links": [
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=5236&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17605&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17606&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=6380&request_locale=en"
        ],
        "explanation": "<p>Both ${1} and ${2} have met their activation conditions. However, you cannot activate 2 Optional Trigger effects that Special Summon themselves from hand in the same chain. Both of these effects are Optional Triggers that would have the card that activates it Special Summon itself from the hand. Therefore, only one of these effects can be activated in a chain, not both. I could not find it written in the perfect Rulebook, but it seems to have a precedent in ${3}.</p>",
        "sources": ["Green Baboon's precedent"],
        "sources_links": ["https://db.ygorganization.com/qa#8192"]
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "Player A controls a face-up ${0} and Player B controls a face-up ${1}. Player A would like to activate the 2nd effect of their ${0} by tributing itself to target Player's B ${1} in a attempt to destroy it. Can they activate that effect and if so, how does it resolve?",
        "propositions": ["Player A cannot activate the 2nd effect of ${0}","Player A can activate the 2nd effect of ${0}, but it will be negated by the effect of ${1}","Player A can activate the 2nd effect of ${0}, and ${1} will be destroyed"],
        "correct": 2,
        "cards": ["Dinowrestler Pankratops", "Skill Drain"],
        "links": [
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=13896&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=5740&request_locale=en"
        ],
        "explanation": "<p>Unless specifically prevented to do so by another effect or restriction, a Monster whose effects are negated can still activate its effects, provided activation requirements are met and costs can be paid. Costs will be paid, and the effect negated at resolution. ${1} reminds you of that in brackets, but that's not specific to ${1}, it applies to all cards that negate the effects of Monsters. So Player A can activate the effect of their ${0}.</p><p>To know how it resolves, it is important to note how ${1} is worded. It negates the effects of Monsters on the field <i class=\"boldUnderline\">while they are on the field</i>. Meaning that as soon as a Monster leaves the field, its effects are no longer negated. In this case, ${0}' effect was activated and resolves on the field, but since it is no longer on the field to be negated, ${1} will be destroyed.</p><p>I would have loved to find a specific ruling entry to illustrate that, but I couldn't find one on ygorg's database.</p>",
        "sources": [],
        "sources_links": []
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Player A controls a face-up ${0} and a face-up ${1}. If that ${0} is used as Link material while the effect of ${1} is applying, is it banished?",
        "propositions": ["Yes","No"],
        "correct": 0,
        "cards": ["Floowandereeze & Robina","Skill Drain"],
        "links": [
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=16498&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=5740&request_locale=en"
        ],
        "explanation": "<p>${1} only negates the effects of Monsters <i class=\"boldUnderline\">while they are face-up on the field</i>. The effect of ${0} that banishes it when it leaves the field is not an effect that applies while on the field, but rather an effect that applies while the card is moving from the field to a new location. Therefore, it cannot be negated by ${1} and ${0} will be banished.</p>",
        "sources": ["Robina and Skill Drain interaction"],
        "sources_links": ["https://db.ygorganization.com/qa#23305"]
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "Player A activates ${0}, and Player B responds with ${1}. After returning to an open gamestate, can Player A activate their second ${0}?",
        "propositions": ["Yes", "No"],
        "correct": 0,
        "cards": ["Primeval Planet Perlereino", "Solemn Judgment"],
        "links": [
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17462&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=4861&request_locale=en"
        ],
        "explanation": "<p>${0} specifically mentions \"You can only <i class=\"boldUnderline\">activate</i> 1 ${0} per turn\". That means that if its activation is specifically negated, it is possible to activate a second one, since that first activation \"never happened\". And ${1} specifically negates the activation of a Spell Card, therefore a second ${0} can be activated in the same turn.</p>",
        "sources": ["Yugipedia page on Once per turns"],
        "sources_links": ["https://yugipedia.com/wiki/Once_per_turn#%22Only_once_per_turn%22"]
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "Player A controls a face-up ${0}, and activates ${1}. Which of the follwing cards or effects <i class=\"boldUnderline\">cannot</i> Player B activate in reponse?",
        "propositions": ["The 1st effect of ${2}", "The 1st effect of ${3}", "${4} (declaring \"Fusion\")", "None of the above"],
        "correct": 3,
        "cards": ["Branded Lost", "Branded Fusion", "Ash Blossom & Joyous Spring", "Herald of Green Light", "Dimensional Barrier"],
        "links": [
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17065&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17066&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=12950&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=6693&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=12668&request_locale=en"
        ],
        "explanation": "<p>${0} prevents the activation of ${1} from being negated, but doesn't specifically prevents a player from responding to the activation, even with an effect that would attempt to negate it. Therefore, all the aforementionned ards can be activated in response, even if the effect of ${3} won't be applied since it can't negate the activation of ${1}.</p>",
        "sources": ["Ash and Green Light can be activated in that case"],
        "sources_links": ["https://db.ygorganization.com/qa#23472"]
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Player A controls a face-up ${0}, and activates ${1}. From the following cards that Player B can activate in response, which of them will <i class=\"boldUnderline\">not</i> cause ${1} to be negated/resolve without effect?",
        "propositions": ["The 1st effect of ${2}", "The 1st effect of ${3}", "${4} (declaring \"Fusion\")", "None of the above"],
        "correct": 1,
        "cards": ["Branded Lost", "Branded Fusion", "Ash Blossom & Joyous Spring", "Herald of Green Light", "Dimensional Barrier"],
        "links": [
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17065&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=17066&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=12950&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=6693&request_locale=en",
            "https://www.db.yugioh-card.com/yugiohdb/card_search.action?ope=2&cid=12668&request_locale=en"
        ],
        "explanation": "<p>${0} specifically prevents the activation of ${1} from being negated, therefore if ${3} is chained to it, its effet won't be applied and ${1} will resolve normally. ${2} only negates the effect, so it won't be blocked by ${0} and the effect of ${1} will be negated. ${4} doesn't negate any activations or Spell effect so it can freely be chained, and prevent the Fusion Summon altogether, so ${1} will resolve without effect.</p>",
        "sources": ["Ash will negate the effect and Green Light's effect won't apply"],
        "sources_links": ["https://db.ygorganization.com/qa#23472"]
    }
]